<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here followeth a true relation or some of the sufferings inflicted upon the servrnts [sic] of the Lord, who are called Quakers by this generation of evil-doers as will appear by the fruits of the schollars and proctors of the University of Oxford, who from the very first appearance of the Lord amongst his people in Oxford, until this time, hath manifested their fruits, and of what stock and generation they are, which fruits now are laid open, that all may see their wickednesse, and may depart from them and their evil works, least they partake of their judgements.</title>
            <author>Haward, Jeremiah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1547</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15016</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12005832</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12005832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52310</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43408)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52310)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 565:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here followeth a true relation or some of the sufferings inflicted upon the servrnts [sic] of the Lord, who are called Quakers by this generation of evil-doers as will appear by the fruits of the schollars and proctors of the University of Oxford, who from the very first appearance of the Lord amongst his people in Oxford, until this time, hath manifested their fruits, and of what stock and generation they are, which fruits now are laid open, that all may see their wickednesse, and may depart from them and their evil works, least they partake of their judgements.</title>
                  <author>Haward, Jeremiah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Jeremiah Haward [&amp; 7 others].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52310:1"/>
            <head>Here followeth a true RELATION OF Some of the Sufferings inflicted upon the ſervrnts of the Lord, who are called QUAKERS, By this generation of Evil-doers, as will appear by the fruits of the Schollars and Proctors of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> who from the very firſt appearance of the Lord amongſt his people in <hi>Oxford,</hi> until this time, hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted their fruits, and of what ſtock and generation they are, which fruits now are laid open, that all may ſee their Wickedneſſe, and may depart from them and their evil Works, leaſt they partake of their judgements.</head>
            <p>WHen firſt the ſervants of the Lord was brought into this City of <hi>Oxford,</hi> to warn people to repentance and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, this generation of Schollars and Profeſſors, unmoderate, untemperate, like bruit beaſts, appeared in much envie and rage, and ſhewed it forth By cruel mockings and ſtonings; two of the hand-maids of the Lord, <hi>Elizabeth Fletcher,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Homes,</hi> were driven by the Schollars into <hi>Johns</hi> Colledge, and there haled by them to the pump, and the Schollars pumped water in their necks, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto their mouths ſo long a time, that they were almoſt ſtifled to death, and dr<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed and the ſame time, took one of the maids, and bound her aboue the knees, and ſet her upon head, and ſaid they would pump the other end. This was the bruitiſh Schollars, and here was their immodeſty and ill-behaviour, which ſhews their breeding, and which is a ſhame to Chancellors, Proctors and Fellows: Is this your government? Is this the fruit of your teaching, like a company of ſporters? They ſhould have been patterns of ſoberneſſe. And preſently after this wicked act, they bound them arm to arm, and drawed them up and down <hi>Johns Colledge,</hi> and dragged them into a pool, and alſo a company of Schollars took one of the maids, <hi>Elizabeth Fletcher,</hi> and threw her over a grave ſtone, and tumbled her into a grave, where a corps was to be laid, and with the violence of that thruſt, over the grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, ſhe received a hurt in her ſide, which was not recovered till her
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52310:2"/>departure out of the body, in ſo much, that we heard her ſay ſeveral times, ſhe ſhould carry it to her grave, ſince which time ſhe is lately dead. Here's murder and blood lies upon them, mad people, the Schollars; which <hi>Johns Colledge,</hi> and the Town ought to be fined for not taking hold on murderers, who murder the innocent; here is the fruits of their fathers, who perſecuted and ſtoned Chriſt &amp; the Apoſtles; and ſo not like to the Apoſtles nor Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Love your enemies; and ſhew mercy, and be mercifull, as your heavenly Father is merciful:</hi> But like unto the <hi>Jewes</hi> that perſecuted and haled the Apoſtles out of the Synagogues, that neither knew the Father nor the Son, <hi>Joh</hi> 16. and ſo continuing their cruelty upon all in <hi>Oxford,</hi> in whom the appearance of God was found, that when friends have been moved of the Lord to go to their Steeple-houſes, they have been drawn out by the hair of the head, and beat, and ſtoned, and ſome of the Schollars have cried, Never let them go home alive; and ſaid, Pump them, and ſtone them to death: And a Proctor, and a company of Schollars (becauſe friends would not go from their own meeting) haled out a friend by the hair of the head, and forced others our of friends meetings, which ſhews they neither regard the Law of God nor man, which is to protect peaceable meeting, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Law of the Nation theſe act: What would their Proctor and Schollars have done, if they had been in <hi>Pauls</hi> dayes, who preached in his own hired houſe? and <hi>Peter,</hi> who taught ſometimes till midnight?</p>
            <p>They came into a meeting in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and drew a friend out by the hair of the head; the Proctor himſelf pulled out <hi>John Shakerly</hi> by the hair, and out of doors, from <hi>Richard Betteris's</hi> houſe, and violently thruſt out others, and ſeveral times the Schollars have thrown ſtones and dirt at friends, and broke the door to pieces, and broke the windows ſeveral times, and took away the key of the door, and knockt tenter-hooks in the key-hole, and (pulled up part of the portch: and this is the fruits of the young Miniſters, the Schollars of <hi>Oxford,</hi> which titles themſelves Miniſters of Chriſt; but are mad, unſavoury, bruitiſh, who are like mad people, or like <hi>Bedlam's;</hi> and when friends have been come into the meeting, or going forth, the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars have ſqueezed them in the paſſage of the door, that ſome hath been hurt, (like wilde horſes and colts) and come into the meeting, and turned up the forms and ſeats which friends ſit upon, rid upon the backs of both men and women, like wilde horſes; and this is the fruits of the Schollars (who are called young Miniſters) in <hi>Oxford,</hi> againſt the people of God, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſturbing their meetings, like wilde Savages, and brought gun-powder, and ſquibs, and fired them, and ſet the room of a ſmoke; and blown among peope under their clothes, like to ſet the houſe on fire, undo undo peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and have ſhot bullets among friends, to knock out their eyes; and this is their wickedneſſe and unſoberneſſe. And the Schollars in <hi>Oxford</hi> came into the meeting among the people of God, ſtamping wildly and rudely, like Tavern fellows crying, <hi>Give us Beer and Tobacco;</hi> and this is the fruits of the Schollars in <hi>Oxford,</hi> among the people of God, who met together to worſhip God in the ſpirit and truth; and this is their carriage in the meeting, which they have born and ſuffered a long time, which is ſhameleſſe, and a grief, which will make ſober people even ſick again; and this is their carriage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, when they are in the ſervice and worſhip of God,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52310:2"/>O! their cruelty is hard to be uttered, as you may read before mentioned, how they bound them with cords, and drew them up and down, and abuſed them in their meeting, and the Schollars have brought ſtrong beer into the meetings, and drunk to friends, and becauſe they have refuſed to drink, have thrown it on their necks, and clothes, and bands; theſe are a company of waſters and deſtroyers of the creation, like a company of tiplers and drunkards. And thus the Schollars are bred up like a company of Tavern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellows, which is a ſhame to the Nation that they ſhould have ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to be their teachers, and ſuch a Nurſery, and ſuch trees to bear ſuch fruits, which well may the Nation be amazed to ſee their fruits brought forth, taking away their goods treble, and haling the people to priſon, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in priſon till death; theſe plants and trees come out of ſuch a nurſery, and puddle, and bad ſtock, And the Schollars has come into the meetings amongſt the people of God, and called for Wenches, or Harlots, like fellows that hunt bad houſes: What would the world think, and the Magiſtrates think, if friends ſhould go into their ſteeple-houſes, and call for ſuch things, which is a ſhame to mention? And the Schollars came into the meetings of the people of God at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and ſung bawdy ſongs, and curſt, and ſwore, theſe were never like Miniſters of Chriſt. And the Schollars ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times came into the meeting blowing and puffing, with Tobacco-pipes in their mouths, curſing, ſwearing, and ſtamping, making the houſe ſhake again, and ſaying, this would make them ſpeak, provoking them to anſwer to their wickedneſs, (but they meekly ſuffered all) and proffered to put their hands under womens aprons, and asked whether the ſpirit was not there; and this is their fruits in the meeting of the people of God, which is a ſhame to the Nation that ſuch bad, looſe, idle fellows ſhould be maintained, who were like hawkers and hunters, riotous fellows, which are bred up in pride and ungodlineſs, which is a grief to all ſober people, to ſee ſuch a Cage of unclean ſpirits; And ye that are called wiſe men of the Nation, and Governors, is it not a diſhonour to you to ſuffer ſuch things? And the Schollars have come into the meeting to act <hi>Tobit</hi> and his dog and one of them divided his filthy ſtuff into uſes &amp; points, after the manner of the Prieſts; and another raiſed doctrines of a Tinker, and a cobler, and many more wicked actions, by mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſcoffings, and filthy language, which would be too tedious to relate, and a ſhame to modeſty, and ſo loathſom and filthy, and alſo a ſhame to lay open ſuch things as have been by them uttered, juſt like a company of Mountibanks and Stage-players: Are theſe a good ſavour of young Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that muſt go out to be teachers in the Nations? O loathſom and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable! Such wicked fruits and acts which is hard to relate! Theſe are like unto the croaking frogs ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and like unto the locuſts that came out of the ſmoke of the bottomleſs pit, bred there, which goes up and down in ſwarms: And theſe Schollars has been ſo ſhameleſs that after the meeting they have preſſed in by violence, and took meat off from the table; came into the houſe of a friend where the meeting was, and took the bread, and the pottage out of the pot like greedy dogs, and ſapping them up; and this is the carriage of the Schollars among the people of God, which they have ſuffered patiently, and this has been their ſhameleſs car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; and ſtopt a friends mouth like to have ſtragled him in the meeting,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52310:3"/>and threw down the woman of the houſe, and this is the fruits of the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: And have ſtoln or taken away books out of the houſe and caryed them away; And a friend going to the Proctor to lay ſome of the practices of the Schollars before him, he denyed them Juſtice, not correcting them; the friend told him that the people were almoſt ſpoiled; &amp; he ſaid he would have nothing to do with them, as much as to ſay, he would tollerates the ſchollars: And an other ſcholar came into the meeting, and cryed out, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, ye wicked people of the Lord. And this is their wickedneſſe, which was never the like heard of, which they make but ſport of, yet theſe muſt have the name of young Miniſters of the Goſpel, and the ſchollars bear the maid of the houſe where the meeting is, and have forced by violence divers times into the houſe, and ſaid they would be there in ſpite of her teeths which things have been done at other times out of the meeting; and theſe waies, of the ſchollars are bad examples to people, they have carryed ſtool out of the houſe, broke down the wall, &amp; carryed the key of the door away and brought in a dog in a meeting time, in deriſion to friends, and this to diſturb the people of God, and this was their cruelty; and bad the dog ſpeak, and punched him to make him howle; and another dog was brought in by the Schollars, and threw up and downe at friends in their meeting; and theſe are their wicked fruits, like Hunts-men, <hi>Eſau's</hi> brood and ſtock, and this hath been their actions like a company of bruits: And ſome have ſtrived by their filthy actions, (becauſe friends would not anſwer their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy wickedneſſe) to make friends ſpeak, &amp; ſeeing they would not, have by force tryed open a friends mouth, to know whether he had a tongue to ſpeak: and others of the Schollars have plucked a friend by the beard and noſe; and have took a friend by the hand, and ſhook her ſo much that they ſprained her Arme, being rude, wicked, and mad: And theſe ſchollars have been ſo rude and wicked, that when any Miniſter of the Lord have been ſpeaking, they have made ſuch a noiſe in his time of ſpeaking, with whooting, yelling, and laughing, and filthy geſtures, on purpoſe to draw peoples minds forth into their image and likeneſſe, who have had deſires to hear the truth, and have uſed wicked actions to keep their minds from it.</p>
            <p>One of the ſervants of the Lord going from a meeting to his own dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and going by <hi>Iohns Colledge,</hi> a great company of Schollars drew him into their Colledge, and forced him up into their Hall; and by main ſtrength and much violence thruſt him into a Chair, and then uſed abominable and wicked words, to have drawn the friends mind our of the fear of the Lord; but when they could not prevail, they brought beer, and like ſlober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laughing beaſts &amp; ſwine, proffered to pour it down his neck, and ſtruck, and beat him with many grievous blows, and pinched him, in ſo much as he was amazed, and natural ſenſe taken away, for a time, with their crulty; and this man about that time, had not eaten a bit of bread in ten days time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very weak, and they thruſt pins into his fleſh, and pinehed him, and kept him in there with many wicked ſcoffs, asking him whether the ſpirit did not move him now: (and thus did the Jews and Prieſts to Chriſt, and then had him propheſie who ſmote him) theſe are the ſame ſeed. And they had him preach or ſing a ſong, or tell a tale, or let a fart; and this is the ſport of the Schollars, that they make of the ſervants of the Lord, which is a ſhame to modeſty and is this a good report of the young Miniſters which ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52310:3"/>go into the Nation? but the friend being kept from fulfilling any of their wicked deſires, ſuſtained much wrong from them, and then three or four of the chief of the Colledge, came to the ſaid friend, and bad him be gon, and pulled him down from that company, but left him among as bad a company of Schollars; and as the ſaid friend was paſſing, to goe our of that wicked crew, he ſeeing ſome of the chief of the Colledge, ſpake a word to them of their cruel actions, and one of the chief of them came and kicked him with his foot, a bad him be gone. Oh mercileſſe cruelty now in the fruits of theſe, when the chief are ſo bruitiſh, and uncivil, what ſhall be gathered of the reſt of them that are under them? And a company of ſchollars have come into the meeting, walking ſtamping, ſtareing, when friends have been met together to wait upon the Lord, on purpoſe to diſturb them. Some of theſe things before mentioned have been laid before the Rulers and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors of ſeveral Colledges in <hi>Oxford,</hi> to this end that they might ſee their fruits, and that for the time to come they might be reſtrained from ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil courſes; but as yet we can ſee no end of their wickedneſſe. So in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto the Lord we have laid open theſe things to the view of them that fears God, and moderate and ſober people, that they may ſee whether the carriage of ſuch be fit to make Miniſters of Chriſt, knowing of a truth we muſt fill up the meaſure of his ſufferings, who is the captain of our ſalvation, (not rendring evill for evil) by ſuch a generation as theſe are, ungodly, illiterate in the truth; but the rather have indured with patience theſe grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous mocking, ſcoffings and contradictions of wicked and ungodly men, &amp; beating, and abuſes from time to time, that the mouths of all gain-ſayers might be ſtopped, when the Lord our god ſhall come forth to give righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgement on every one of them, for the work done in the body. And theſe things we leave to the conſideration of all moderate ſober men, to judge whether theſe actions be ſober, comely, moderate, and of a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that be before mentioned; and whether ſuch actions of fruits, from ſuch as before mentioned, be fit for to make Miniſters for Chriſt, who was far from doing wrong, or hurting any creature, and theſe are far from his minde and the Apoſtles, who wreſtled not with fleſh and blood; nor ſtrik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and abuſing the creatures, &amp; how unlike to them theſe are that wrongs friends in their meetings, and brings in their dogs &amp; their drink, throwing it about upon friends cloathes, bands, necks, with tobaco-pipes in their mouthes and making plaies, and ſtamping, and calling, give me drink, and tobacco, and wenches, and Whores, and this is the fruites of the ſchollars of <hi>Oxford,</hi> raging about the door, pulling down the porch, breaking the windowes, like the <hi>Sodomites</hi> that crucified the juſt. So their filthy bruitiſh carriage is ſeen, which never was heard the like, their tricks, jeſts, plaies, ſports with their beer, tobacco-pips, ſtamping, leaping; &amp; their ſtriking of friends, as knowing that friends will not lift up a hand againſt them. And the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars comes into the meeting of friends with all their gaudy attire, with rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans and cuffs dreſſed and daubed like fidlers and ſtage-players, which have not the garments of ſober men. And the ſaid ſchollars that comes into the meetings, would turne up the hats of women as they ſat in the meeting, in their aſſemblies, and ſtare in their faces to provoke them, with bad language. Now you may ſee how theſe regards the word of the Lord, as their unſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe declares it.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52310:4"/>
            <p>Now are the people as they were in the dayes of <hi>Iob, poyſon drinks up their ſpirits.</hi> And now are the people as they were in the daies of the Prophets, which drink up iniquity as water and in that doth rejoyce: And now doth the people drink up ſcorning as water; for look in every Town, market and county, you ſhall ſee a company of ſcorners, and people drink it up, &amp; he that is the apteſt and the wittieſt, that will pleaſe people beſt, that they drink up like water, ther's their joy: nay you ſhall ſee the young Miniſters &amp; Prieſts ſcorne, and the other will drink up their ſcorne like water; ſo the one ſcorneth, and the other drinketh it up, and the other doth iniquity, and the other drinketh that up as the Oxe drinketh water, and the poyſon thereof drinketh up their ſpirits; and how all people hath, and doth prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice evil works upon their beds, and when the daylight cometh, doth act it? Now theſe ſcholars of <hi>Oxford</hi> are like unto the raging <hi>Sodomites,</hi> who rounded <hi>Lots</hi> houſe in temporal <hi>Sodom,</hi> which God delivered them out of their hands, &amp; in ſpiritual <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> that is, darkneſſe and filthineſs. Now the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and royal feed and Plants of the Lord God, has the ſpiritual <hi>Sodomites</hi> &amp; the ſpiritual <hi>Aegyptians</hi> to deal with, which are ſpiritually blind, which cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifies Chriſt. Now theſe ſpiritual <hi>Sodomites</hi> have the ſcriptures, the ſheeps cloathing, but cannot deceive the Elect. Now the ſpiritual <hi>Sodomites</hi> &amp; <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> will tell the people that they have the Original, and <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> is the Original, and they are the Orthodox men that have it, and the Pillars of the Church; but <hi>Moſes</hi> will tell the ſpiritual <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> that all the World was of one language before <hi>Babel;</hi> and he that did begin to build <hi>Babel,</hi> came out of <hi>Ham's</hi> ſtock, whom God confounded into many languages: But they that are the royal and elect ſeed, will tell you <hi>In the beginning was the word,</hi> before <hi>Babel</hi> was. And <hi>Luke</hi> the Evangeliſt will tell you (ſpiritual <hi>Sodomites</hi> &amp; <hi>Aegyptians</hi> that tels the World <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> is the Original) that <hi>Pilate</hi> the murtherer and perſecutor ſet that upon Chriſt, ſo there ſtands your original over the juſt, and he is your Orthodox man and your pillar, and he knew not ſcripture, nor Chriſt the juſt; but murthered him, he who had the original, who ſet it upon Chriſt when he had murthered him, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.38 [mark] a ſuperſcription was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten over Chriſt is: <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin;</hi> here <hi>Pilate</hi> and the <hi>Jewes</hi> had the Original (as you call it) that killed the juſt (Can you hear this, Prieſts?) and he could not open ſcriptures: did <hi>Luke</hi> ſay theſe were the Original that was ſet on top of Chriſt? Now the Original is the Word which was in the beginning, but your many languages is ſince the beginning, and there ſtands your Original. Mark, again you Doctors and ſcholars, Chriſt ſaid falſe prophets ſhould come, And Antichriſt ſhould come, they that were againſt Chriſt, that if it ſhould be poſſible ſhould deceive the Elect, which falſe prophets ſhould be inwardly ravening, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.24, <hi>chap.</hi> Chriſt ſaid they ſhould come to his diſciples, and in 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. chap. and 4. and. <hi>John</hi> ſaid they were come, and went forth from them into the world: and in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> all the World went after them; ſo theſe inwardly ravening from the ſpirit of God, having the ſheeps cloathing, having gotten a head, turned againſt the Saints that was in the ſpirit of God, and killed them, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came them, and when they had overcome the Saints, power was given to the beaſt over all Nations, Tongues, and Kindreds; marke, ye Doctors,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52310:4"/>Miniſters and young ſcholars; what, hath the beaſt power over your Tongues, Orthodox men, original? Yes, Why not the beaſt power over the Tongues, as well as <hi>Pilate</hi> that killed the juſt? So the beaſt, over the Tongues, and Orthodox men; ye Doctors and ſchollars whoſe Original is Tongues, ſo not the ſpirit, [mark] <hi>Pilate</hi> your elder brother that ſet them on top of Chriſt; was <hi>Pilate</hi> a preacher of the Goſpel, that murtherer, that had the Tongues, and ſet them on top of Chriſt? Was the beaſt a preacher of the Goſpel, that killed the Saints, that had power over the Tongues? What o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your Orthodox men? over our original has the beaſt power? Yea, who turnes againſt the Saints and kils them that kept the Teſtimony of Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7 and the beaſt, and his marks, and his hornes, and his Images which turns againſt the ſaints; and ſee how you Orthodox men are raging about the doors of the Saints, which the beaſt has power over, how you are raging about the doors of the Saints, like a cage of unclean birds, a habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of unclean ſpirits. Is not <hi>Babylon</hi> faln, and become a habitation of Devils, and the Whore ſhe ſits upon the beaſt, and all Nations have drunk of her fornication, and the Kings of the earth have commited fornication with the Whore, and hath corrupted the whole Earth, and the whore ſits upon the waters, and the waters are Nations, multitudes, and Tongues? Marke Prieſts, is the Whore on the Tongues? what, our miniſters? what, our orthodox men? what our Original? is the whore on them? and are they waters? Yes, <hi>Iohn</hi> tells you they are waters, <hi>Rev</hi> 17. Come Prieſts let's reckon with you; Have you not told people that falſe Prophets are come but now? and they muſt come to <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. And what has the beaſt power over you, and the beaſt upon you, and the whore upon you, and are they come but now? Now Prieſt you are diſcovered to be the falſe Prophets. what has the beaſt power over you, and over your Tongues, and have you not told us that Chriſt would be with you to the end of the world, and the beaſt and whore has power over you, as <hi>Pilate</hi> had over the tongues? And ſo you have got the ſheeps cloathings, and ravened from the ſpirit of God; and the beaſt hath killed the Saints and the Prophets, and the man-child was caught up to God, and the woman fled into the wilderneſſe, and the whore has drunk the blood of the Saints, that has power over the Tongues; Orthodox men, pillars of the Church, and there came up the falſe Church, the whore, when the true woman fled into the wilderneſſe; but the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great whore ſhall come again, and the marriage of the Lamb ſhall be known again, the bride and the Lambs wife: And <hi>Iohn</hi> calls you waters, as you may read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. and 17. chap. Which ſcriptures you can never get over. Alack for you poor ſilly ones! has not the Church been in the wilderneſſe ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles? And has not the beaſt fought his honour? And was not the cry again, <hi>Fear God, and give glory to him?</hi> and muſt not the beaſt be taken, the falſe Prophet and the Whore, and caſt alive into the Lake of fire, and <hi>Babylon</hi> confounded, and the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great whore come? and this is witneſſed in theſe our daies. So <hi>Babel</hi> is the beginning of Tongues, on the top of Chriſt, <hi>Pilate</hi> he ſet them, the murtherer and perſecutor; and the beaſt, the whore has power over them, and ſits upon them. So hear is the path of the Orthodox men, that they work in <hi>Babel,</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> the beaſt, and the whore, that murthers
<pb facs="tcp:52310:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>and kills the Saints and Chriſt, who cries the tongues is the Original, which wants the Original, the Word which was before <hi>Babel</hi> was, and now Prieſts we ſhall teach you, the beaſt hath power over tongues, and the Whore, and <hi>Pilate</hi> that ſet them a-top of Chriſt; but Chriſt is riſen that was before <hi>Babel</hi> was, or <hi>Pilate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and is, when beaſt, and Whore, and <hi>Babel</hi> is not; ſo he that was dead, is alive, and lives for evermore, and will ſtain your glory and pride, who has told the world that <hi>Hedrew, Greek,</hi> &amp; <hi>Latin</hi> was the Original, but he is riſen who will ſtain your glory, mar your pride, and deface your beauty which you have had in your naturals, and the Goſpel muſt be preached again to all Nations, Tongues and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reds, and all that dwell upon the Earth, What, (ſay you Orthodox men) have we not had the Goſpel before now? Nay, you ravened from the ſpirit of God, you had the ſheeps cloathing, and ſo ſet up that for your Original, that <hi>Pilate</hi> ſet on Chriſts you ravened from the ſpirit of God, who went our from the Apoſtles, and ſo went into the World, and ſet up the Tongues to be the Original, which the beaſt has power over, which killed the Saints; ſo you ravened from the power of God which is the Goſpel, <hi>Rom:</hi> 1. ſo the beaſt ſhall be taken, your Maſter, and the Whore, your mother, and yee the falſe Prophets, and the old Dragon your Father, ſhall be taken alive, with <hi>Babylon</hi> that you ſheltered in, and all caſt alive into the lake that burns; and the everlaſting Goſpel ſhall be preached again to them that dwel upon the Earth, which is the power of God; and now it is going forth again, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Lord in the higheſt for ever: And the Schollars of <hi>Oxford</hi> are like Iewes, the baſer ſort that made an uproar and aſſaulted the houſe of <hi>Jaſon;</hi> lewd fellowes, the baſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſort, and brought <hi>Jaſon</hi> before the Rulers, and ſaid they turned the World upſide down: Now ſee, the lambs and the ſheep were alwaies ſufferers; ſee who aſſaulted <hi>Lot's</hi> houſe, and who was it at <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's</hi> houſe, but the rude fellowes, and who at <hi>Rich. Betetis's</hi> Houſe in <hi>Oxford</hi> that pulled up the porch, and broke the Windowes, came in with dogs and Tobacco pipes but rude ſchollars and who would have thought the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of <hi>Oxford</hi> would have come to Rich Bete<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is's houſe to aske for laſſes, whores, wenche<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? ſurely they miſt the houſe &amp; this is the work and the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſer fellowes in the nation who would think that theſe ſchollars ſhould grow to ſuch a hight of luſtfulneſſe, fleſhlineſſe and ungodlineſſe. And who would have thought that the ſcholars of <hi>Oxford</hi> had been like ſuch Tavern fellowes, to come into <hi>Rich. Beteris's</hi> houſe and cry give me ſome Ale, give me ſome tobacco, ſtamping up and down? ſurely they <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re more like Swine, with their noiſe in the though, then like Miniſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo hot in their luſt of ungodlineſſe, that they tumble and lye do<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the mire, and are ſaid to call for Laſſes; and whores, and wenches among the people ſo God; ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rely they are worſe then the common ſavage beaſts; and Doctor Owin <hi>who hath ſpewed out ſome thing, and vomited up a lothſome thing againſt the people of God called Quakers; which loathſome vomit is enough to poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſeveral people that is not in the wiſdome what to eat, which vomit is like unto the works of his fellowes abovementioned? So ſee whoſe ſteps you walke in; and what do you think<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they that are come into the word of God, cannot ſee over the tongues and Pilate, and Babel, and theſe ſchollars alſo, they do not know the word in the beginning which abideth for ever, the beaſt and the falſ prophet doth not, but they that are come to the word doth, and are in that which doth endure.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Jeremiah Haward.</item>
                     <item>Abraham Allin.</item>
                     <item>Thomas Ryland</item>
                     <item>Henry Traine,</item>
                     <item>Lawrence Willyer.</item>
                     <item>Thomas Swan.</item>
                     <item>Alex Green</item>
                     <item>Abra Badger.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
